<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The MuppetGate Conspiracy</title><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/feeds/technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://muppetgate.github.io/</id><updated>2015-04-26T23:06:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Lightning is Here to Stay</title><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/lightning-is-here-to-stay.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-04-26T23:06:00+02:00</updated><author><name>MuppetGate</name></author><id>tag:muppetgate.github.io,2015-04-26:lightning-is-here-to-stay.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The press loves to talk about Apple. Whether it's their lastest bit of kit, the price of their latest bit of kit, the number of women serving on their board . . . it doesn't matter. Apple generates hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trouble is, in their rush to generate ad clicks, the popular IT press not only miss the subtler points, they often miss the plainly obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last week, Apple announced the rather gorgeous &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/macbook/"&gt;Macbook&lt;/a&gt;, a laptop so thin it ships with shaving foam. Aside from its size and lack of power, the press has also been drawn to the single USB-C port that, in their mind, signifies the end of the lightning interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Why does Apple need Lightning,' the popular IT press cries, 'when they have something almost as good and a lot more universal like USB-C?' &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I think there are a couple of reasons, the most important of which (to Apple anyway) is size. USB-C is dinky, but the lightning connector is dinkier still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="USB-C and lightning compared" src="http://muppetgate.github.io/assets/images/usb-c_sizecompare.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when you're as size-obsessed as Apple, then those few extra millimetres make all the difference. There is also the question of money. Compared to the money it prints selling iPhones, the &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/programs/mfi/"&gt;MFI&lt;/a&gt; programme is, no doubt, a drop in the ocean. But to a company as obsessed with detail as Apple, every drop counts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple recently detailed future plans for the lightning connector at its recent &lt;a href="http://9to5mac.com/2014/11/18/apple-mfi-summit-third-party-products-lightning-port-new-accessories/"&gt;MFI Summit held in China&lt;/a&gt;. The main takeaway was an extension to the programme that will allow third-party vendors to build lightning ports into their own devices. Cupertino also announceed a new low-profile connector which would be suitable for smaller devices such as battery cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while all this was going on, Apple was heavily involved in defining the USB-C spec, making sure they had a say in what goes at the other end of the cable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lightning is something of a smart cable; to ensure its longevity, Apple made the pin assigments programmable, allowing it to adapt to whatever interface came along in the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So rather than USB-C signalling the end of Lightning, I think it is merely another interface that Lightning was designed to cope with.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Technology"></category><category term="Apple"></category></entry></feed>