<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The MuppetGate Conspiracy</title><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/feeds/technology.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://muppetgate.github.io/</id><updated>2015-06-09T05:41:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>WWDC Keynote. The Good, the Bad . . . and the really Weird</title><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/wwdc-keynote-the-good-the-bad-and-the-really-weird.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-09T05:41:00+02:00</updated><author><name>MuppetGate</name></author><id>tag:muppetgate.github.io,2015-06-09:wwdc-keynote-the-good-the-bad-and-the-really-weird.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So another WWDC keynote has come and gone. It definitely wasn't the polished effort of years past, and in places I think the audience was a little bored. (I know I was.)
Right off the bat, I think this was entirely the wrong place to launch the new music service. It needed an event on its own (or preferably, alongside a TV streaming service). Still, there was a lot interesting stuff going on, that was unfortunately raced through so that we could get to the Apple Music bit. Anyway, here are the parts that stood out for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Good&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metal comes to the Mac.&lt;/strong&gt; This is great news, and I love how the company leverages technology from one platform onto the others. Games have become a huge moneyspinner for the iPhone/iPad and it's good to see that Apple is keen to bring this success to the desktop. Could we see the Mac lose the 'crap for gaming' moniker it's been saddled with since Day One?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multi-tasking on the iOS.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, I know: iOS has always had multi-tasking, but Apple are letting the users actually see it. Task-switching lifted straight from OSX and two app running side-by-side. Should be a long-overdue winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swift goes open source.&lt;/strong&gt; This one was a no-brainer. There were a few new language features and compiler optimisations, but Craig Federighi shot through this section like his trousers were on fire. Still, good to see the Swift goodness will soon be available everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Apple Music.&lt;/strong&gt; I didn't say I didn't like it; I just said that this was the wrong venue for the launch. Personally, I think it's huge. The service itself is nothing particularly new, but the focus they've given to unsigned acts is the game-changer. Apple is trying to do for the music world what the App Store did for small, independent developer. I'm hoping this will make it much easier to find and listen to something outside the production line acts that seem to have taken over. I'm actually surprised that the music industry would sign on with this. Sure they're getting their cut, but I wonder if they'll be this happy with it a few years down the line. 
I guess you could argue that this doesn't really cross into their space: they can go on manufacturing acts and will continue to make millions doing so.
Oh, and support for the Android platform? Didn't see that coming!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No new features for OSX.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes, this is a good thing. The fact that they didn't have any real whizz-bang features to announce for OSX El Capitan (doesn't exactly roll off the tongue, does it?) means that they (hopefully) have been taking time out to tighten things up a little. I haven't experienced too many problems myself, but I've heard a lot of complaints about the WiFi. It's always difficult to gauge how serious these problems are; the internet tends to be something of an echo chamber where Apple is concerned. From a user's perspective it's good; let's slow down, consolidate and look at what can be fixed/improved before we dump a whole new set of stuff to learn on to the customer base.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The bad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt; No Apple TV update&lt;/strong&gt; Booo!! Though to be fair, they never promised one. Still, the whole Apple Music section did leave me with the impression that there was something missing, that a few other names (Iovine, Drake) had been rolled out at the last minute to fill some space.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The very, very weird&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, this was the strangest WWDC keynote I've seen in some time.  Jimmy Iovine came on and shouted, Drake came on and rambled, Eddy Cue came on and jigged about like a wannabe DJ. Something was a no-show at the last minute I'd say. But the question still stands: Why announce a music service at a developers conference?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Apple"></category><category term="technology"></category></entry><entry><title>The Black &amp; White World of Apple Journalism</title><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/the-black-white-world-of-apple-journalism.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-31T09:36:00+02:00</updated><author><name>MuppetGate</name></author><id>tag:muppetgate.github.io,2015-05-31:the-black-white-world-of-apple-journalism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;According to the IT pundits, last week's biggest story was the news that Apple's head-of-all-things-tasteful has been promoted. As the man in charge of UI and industrial design, Sir Jonathan Ive was responsible for the day-to-day running of two Apple divisions. In a promotion that was leaked (strangely) through an &lt;a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/apple/11628710/When-Stephen-Fry-met-Jony-Ive-the-self-confessed-fanboi-meets-Apples-newly-promoted-chief-design-officer.html"&gt;in-Telegraph&lt;/a&gt; chat with his good mate Steven Fry, Ive revealed that from July he will be Apple's Chief Design Officer. He'll be doing much the same as he does now, but without having to worry about the operational management stuff. This will free him to focus soley on the thing he loves to do: design. (I can almost hear the wails of Apple's engineering department: 'You want us to fit all of this – into that??')
As well as the existing products such as the iPhone, the Mac, and the Apple Watch, Ive will be blue-skying the future stuff too. He'll also have his eye on the design of the Apple stores (including the furniture, apparently). The day-to-day management of Industrial Design and User Interface Design will be handed over to his newly promoted lieutenants, Richard Howe and Alan Dye:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Alan Dye, Jony Ive and Richard Howe. Picture courtesy of the Daily Telegraph" src="http://muppetgate.github.io/assets/images/ive-crew.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a solid move that makes a lot of sense, but it does seem to have the IT press somewhat confused. To begin with there was the odd business of announcing it in the Telegraph, rather than a US journal, and speaking to all-round good egg and unashamed Apple fan Steven Fry, rather than someone like Walt Mossberg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chances are that Apple wanted to keep the whole thing low-key to prevent the sort of uninformed panic we see in the IT press whenever someone in Cupertino blows their nose. Well, if that was Apple's plan it failed miserably.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple reporting tends to be very black-and-white: It is either the end of days, or the second coming; there is no room for any middle ground because the middle-ground doesn't create ad clicks. So on Sir Jony's promotion we have two schools of thought:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ive is being promoted because he wants to leave Apple (bizarre).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ive is being promoted so he is free to think lofty designery thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IT press has spoken: it HAS to be one of those two. The truth, however, is probably somewhere in the middle where page impressions aren't generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For sure, he'll be  guiding the overall design principles for the company as a whole, and he'll also have significant input on new products going forward. In this regard, his role will be very similar to that of Steve Jobs, which, from what I've read, was the plan all along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, he will be laying the groundwork for those who'll take over after him. Not just the two chaps running  his divisions, but the young UI and industrial designers that the company is taking on now. He'll instill the essence of what makes an Apple product difficult to put down once you've taken it off the display stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The IT press has mixed views on what Apple does best: software, chip design, manufacturing technology, battery research and development. There's plenty to choose from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, what the company does best is succession planning. To the majority of the  press, it was inconceivable that the company would survive after the death of its iconic founder. Some still think it's some sort of abberation that will correct itself any day now. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The company not only survived, it flourished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so while this promotion is about Ive taking on a more Jobsian role at Apple, it is also about what happens afterwards, though that doesn't mean he's leaving any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Apple"></category></entry><entry><title>Microsoft and the Road to OS/2</title><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/microsoft-and-the-road-to-os2.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-12T07:22:00+02:00</updated><author><name>MuppetGate</name></author><id>tag:muppetgate.github.io,2015-05-12:microsoft-and-the-road-to-os2.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Read a great article on &lt;a href="http://arstechnica.co.uk/information-technology/2015/05/android-and-ios-apps-on-windows-what-is-microsoft-doing-and-will-it-work/"&gt;Ars Technica&lt;/a&gt; the other day, which talked about Microsoft's plans to fix the app drought on Windows  by becoming a universal platfrom. The article is well worth a look (along with the comments!), but the gist of it is that Redmond is going to attack the problem from two sides:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Windows for Phones will allow a subset of Android applications to run inside a sandboxed container. What they mean by a 'subset' is anyone's guess right now, but I imagine stuff that needs to run close to the metal will be a non-starter. Microsoft will also be intercepting calls to Google services and replacing them with their own. (Cheeky!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft will be releasing tools to make it easier for developers to port iOS apps to Windows for Phones. Again, we'll have to wait and see what real-world results look like. I'm not a fan of ported apps myself, but if the code was engineered with proper separation of the UI from the engine underneath then Microsoft's tools should make the job easier without impacting  too badly on the user experience. Time will tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first read about this, my initial thought was: &lt;em&gt;How the hell has it come to this?&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface (no pun intended) this looks like an admission of defeat: &lt;em&gt;No one is writing apps for our platform so we've no choice but to entice developers from Android and iOS.&lt;/em&gt; It's quite a fall for the mighty Microsoft, but it is what it is. I remember a similar feeling when Steve Jobs went on stage and announced that &lt;a href="http://www.mac-history.net/apple-history-tv/2008-07-19/macworld-boston-1997-steve-jobs-returns-bill-gates-appeares-on-screen"&gt;Redmond was Apple's new best friend&lt;/a&gt;. The difference back then was that the Apple faithful were up in arms over the deal; this time round, the mood of  Microsoft fans is something closer to a grumbling acceptance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What was, was. This is the reality we're dealing with now, and for tackling that head-on I think Satya Nadella deserves a round of applause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the new development strategy isn't without risks, and the elephant-in-the-breakout-area was succintly exposed in the Ars Technica article: Didn't IBM try this with OS/2?&lt;sup id="sf-microsoft-and-the-road-to-os2-1-back"&gt;&lt;a title="A potted history of OS/2 is available here. Well worth a read!" class="simple-footnote" href="#sf-microsoft-and-the-road-to-os2-1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running Windows software on OS/2 was supposed to provide an incentive to IBM's customers. (It runs Windows software, so where's the risk?). What it actually did was discourage native development. (It runs Windows software, why waste effort writing native software for it?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sure that Nadella is well aware of OS/2's history, and so I'm sure he is aware of the risks involved in running Android apps in much the same way. Still, needs must – and there is a possible hidden benefit: If successful, would this scheme slow development on iOS? If you could target two successful platforms with your Android app, then why not develop there first? It's a thought for a possible future; Windows on the Phone would need to come close to matching the iOS installed base for that to happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, Microsoft's first prong – tools to port from iOS – is not your mother's OS/2 strategy. Windows Phone will not be running iOS apps in a subsystem because that would be a disaster for the platform as a whole. The idea is that if iOS developers can port their apps easily then why wouldn’t they? 
Well, supporting a platform is more than just writing code for it. You need to understand its underpinnings to get the best out of it; you need to understand how it interacts with its user and the other applications installed on the phone. You need to understand what could be causing it to crash when the unported code runs fine elsewhere.It'll need a high level of skill to make sure that your ported application doesn't &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; like a ported application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, nothing's changed: You'll still need to a damn good understanding of every platform your app is running on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So lots of little things, but it's a start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do wonder, however, if there was an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to bring developers to your platform, why not cast your API out to all developers? Microsoft has decades of cross-platform experience which they must be using internally. Why not build the frameworks to run on iOS and Android? For one thing it would be a reward for their own developer community who have waited (not always patiently) for Microsoft to get their mobile act together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;ol class="simple-footnotes"&gt;&lt;li id="sf-microsoft-and-the-road-to-os2-1"&gt;A potted history of OS/2 is available &lt;a href="http://techland.time.com/2012/04/02/25-years-of-ibms-os2-the-birth-death-and-afterlife-of-a-legendary-operating-system/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Well worth a read! &lt;a class="simple-footnote-back" href="#sf-microsoft-and-the-road-to-os2-1-back"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="Microsoft"></category><category term="Apple"></category><category term="Android"></category></entry><entry><title>Lightning is Here to Stay</title><link href="http://muppetgate.github.io/lightning-is-here-to-stay.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-04-26T23:06:00+02:00</updated><author><name>MuppetGate</name></author><id>tag:muppetgate.github.io,2015-04-26:lightning-is-here-to-stay.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The press loves to talk about Apple. Whether it's their lastest bit of kit, the price of their latest bit of kit, the number of women serving on their board . . . it doesn't matter. Apple generates hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trouble is, in their rush to generate ad clicks, the popular IT press not only miss the subtler points, they often miss the plainly obvious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last week, Apple announced the rather gorgeous &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/macbook/"&gt;Macbook&lt;/a&gt;, a laptop so thin it ships with shaving foam. Aside from its size and lack of power, the press has also been drawn to the single USB-C port that, in their mind, signifies the end of the lightning interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'Why does Apple need Lightning,' the popular IT press cries, 'when they have something almost as good and a lot more universal like USB-C?' &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I think there are a couple of reasons, the most important of which (to Apple anyway) is size. USB-C is dinky, but the lightning connector is dinkier still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="USB-C and lightning compared" src="http://muppetgate.github.io/assets/images/usb-c_sizecompare.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And when you're as size-obsessed as Apple, then those few extra millimetres make all the difference. There is also the question of money. Compared to the money it prints selling iPhones, the &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/programs/mfi/"&gt;MFI&lt;/a&gt; programme is, no doubt, a drop in the ocean. But to a company as obsessed with detail as Apple, every drop counts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple recently detailed future plans for the lightning connector at its recent &lt;a href="http://9to5mac.com/2014/11/18/apple-mfi-summit-third-party-products-lightning-port-new-accessories/"&gt;MFI Summit held in China&lt;/a&gt;. The main takeaway was an extension to the programme that will allow third-party vendors to build lightning ports into their own devices. Cupertino also announceed a new low-profile connector which would be suitable for smaller devices such as battery cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And while all this was going on, Apple was heavily involved in defining the USB-C spec, making sure they had a say in what goes at the other end of the cable. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lightning is something of a smart cable; to ensure its longevity, Apple made the pin assigments programmable, allowing it to adapt to whatever interface came along in the future. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So rather than USB-C signalling the end of Lightning, I think it is merely another interface that Lightning was designed to cope with.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Technology"></category><category term="Apple"></category></entry></feed>